so for example another another way to do
a guided contemplation
well in a way that matters to us
developing wisdom at least would be to
to ponder on various mental states they
usually are something that people don't
want to think about so something
disagreeable that's why their the
contemplation of death in the Buddhist
practice is wonderful well the quickest
the sharpest obviously it's risky ways
of developing wisdom and abandoning
experiencing this passion towards
existence so you know there are other
ways as well that you could other themes
that you can dwell on and that can help
you they were the same dispassion but
it's not enough to think about it once
or twice just have a thought or
something I mean on some occasion I
suppose yeah like if the conditions are
right so to speak you're in the right
frame of mind one thought is enough to
establish the theme they will have a
deeper emotional significance on you but
then this one is early last and if
you're only in establishing your
practice or contemplation upon that
feeling of quick inspiration then you
won't be really doing the work so you
want to be able to to think and ponder
on things even if you don't necessarily
feel like doing so so in this in this
particular instance the the theme you
could be developing for example is the
sense of safety like just whatever
whatever situation you living in the
sense of safety which is obviously
inseparable from your existential sense
itself so you want to well start looking
into it to begin with so ask yourself
safety safety what is Safety mean for me
do I feel safe now
if the answer is yes which problem was
recalled as a yes then
ask yourself a further question is that
sense of safety something I can always
have a say in I can always be in charge
or or is it sort of I can only kind of
my efforts can only approximate that
result of safety as in our hope for the
best
so again as I mentioned many times in
other you know it talks you don't wanna
be like just asking questions wrong
answer you ask the question on safety in
this case they will then make you think
about how you feel now what does that
say to mean for you so what is the
safety mean freedom
you can let that question and do it and
think about it there's no right or wrong
answer it's really just clarified what's
already there sin society that you're
talking about but what does that mean
what what constitutes safety in your
experience it is an absence of physical
discomfort of physical threat emotional
absence of emotional discomfort both
yeah that's probably it
but then ask yourself so what is then in
common what is the common thread through
to physical discomfort emotional
discomfort mental discomfort
what is absence of it means safety so
what is the common absence in these
phenomena they determine your sense of
current safety so its absence of
unpleasant feeling on that fundamental
existential level make you know you can
be experiencing some annoyance but
fundamentally that doesn't compromise
your sense of safety but now you want to
be dwelling on the sense of safety why
is it not compromised
is it because you have a say in it why
do you feel safe I mean your heart can
stop any like next second and that's it
your safety is gone so then your input
in your own safety is very relative but
that's what what an ignorant mind the
mind it's not devoted to training that's
what it forgets everybody knows that you
are fundamentally not in control but
everybody chooses to not dwell on it
because it's too unpleasant it brings
anxiety dread discomfort all sorts of
things and that's the ignorant that's a
video choosing to not think about
certain things that pertain to the
nature resistance so if you don't start
choosing against that grain of avoiding
thinking about things that cause me
anxiety that's how you start and you
stop ignoring it right with the absence
of ignorance the attitude of in
you will you will become more and more
familiar with the nature of those
phenomena which means you will be less
and less passionate about life life as
you know it because life as you know it
depends upon ignorance of certain things
that's why the mind is devoted to
ignorance is the mind that finds join
sensuality defines justification in
anger that finds there finds peace in
distraction but if you approve the
ignorance none of these three three
things can be manifested in or can
continue their uninterrupted
manifestation in your life it means you
still be alive but now the life will
have a different value for you so sense
of safety again it's it's it's something
quite fundamental very important to all
of us but something that pretty much
everyone takes for granted until it's
too late
usually so you don't want to wait for
that you want to start questioning it
and challenging it while you still can
while it's still while you still can
help make a choice about it so sense of
safety means absence of displeasure
threatening things they threaten my life
but all order the life I'm used to it
see like for a person who is fully
devoted and engage in sensuality not
having access to essential objects is
already filled feels like a threat
exists natural threat somebody who will
be drawn from sensuality doesn't devote
his time just to just with sensual
thoughts and actions he won't feel
threatened if he has no access to that
which he is indifferent towards but then
he might feel threatened toward
something that he does depend on that's
like in the suitors we discussed it
before as well when then when the monkey
dwells in the forest he develops his
mind upon the perceptions of the forest
then when he goes to the village nothing
in the village well nothing that he sees
smells tastes artists editor in the
village can disturb his mind which is
established upon the perceptions of the
forest but in the Buddha says if
something were to happen to the forest
his mind would
disturbed so then he sees that and then
he goes a step higher
what is that forest then what is higher
than the forest it's perception of Earth
or you can even say perception of life
or perception of the living body
mindfulness of the body you establish
your mind upon that then doesn't matter
the circumstance doesn't matter the
change of the circumstances whether it's
adverse or positive or whatever you
would remain unaffected because your
mind has not been cultivating dependence
upon those things so that's why you want
to start questioning the sense of safety
because for most people starting point
is that that sense of safety is
proliferated too far out as in it's not
just your health in your life that you
depend on it's your health your life
your work your family your friends
people you want to do what you tell them
to do access to full access to
distraction access to central object
that's where people's minds are that
that how far out so any of those things
anything less than those things they
would be experiencing a degree of threat
like threat to the lifestyle that I know
or which is more correctly to say threat
to the life study that I take for
granted and assume but you want to
reflect that those things will
inevitably they have to be taken away
from you so you better start dwelling
and that before it's too late
rather than waiting for them to be taken
away from you and then you think somehow
because if you haven't been dealing with
those things while they were in front of
you what makes you think you'll be able
to deal with them when they are removed
against your will it's too late it's
like being able to do with whole I don't
know 300 kilos in your back suddenly
never ever made the effort to put weight
on your back and endure it just hope
that when it comes you be able to hold
it well that's quite a quite a quite a
foolish attitude so your meditation your
contemplation can be reflecting upon how
far is your sense of safety proliferated
how much did you take for granted
basically of your life of your sense
experience of people around you it quiet
and then and then start to start
training it in bringing your mind back
to things that that are not so much out
of your control so you can ask where is
my sense of say what makes me feel safe
right here right now if if I were to get
sick we're experiencing xiety yes that
means then that there is a degree of
threat in sickness which means my safety
is is overreaching my sense of safety
because you can only do so much to
control to have input in your health but
fundamentally it's not on you yet
doesn't mean you neglect your health but
don't use the amount of input you have
in your health don't use that to develop
a notion that you are in charge of your
health so don't ignore the fact that you
can never ever step outside of it and
become the full complete master and if
you have any doubt about that just ask
just imagine getting sick would you be
affected and if the answer is yes
emotionally mentally I will be affected
I would you know be afraid or whatever
depending on what sickness it is means I
am threatened by it
and if there is if there is an
experience of threat can only affect you
because your assumption is it's taking
up things that are not in your control
that's it so if you stop taking things
that don't belong to you including your
own health your body your whole life and
everything else that comes out of it
nothing can threaten you there is no
basis for that threat to land you could
see nothing has changed in things you
still have your life you're still alive
our hunt is still alive so nothing has
changed yet everything has changed
because your attitude has changed so you
don't need to rewrite the significance
of things like liability to illness
stays for puja name for another hunt
it's just because Papagena is taking his
life for granted he said
he's functioning senses as fully mine
then he will be affected when illness
comes but Aaron has removed his attitude
not the senses or day liability and
everything else he has just removed his
assumption of ownership and that's why
he is he has no fear he cannot be
threatened by anything and also in a
practical level you can if you dwell for
example on the nature of your body
natural life mindfulness of death means
you are then establishing your mind upon
something that's that's better
then then depending or trying to control
the circumstances for example okay I
don't care what happens over there but I
care what happens in my house I care
what happens to my house I care to who
moves and becomes my neighbor or all
these things but if all you care even
when you are in your house is about
mindfulness of the body mindfulness of
liability to to death or sickness and so
on even even if things happen to your
house to your own bedroom to your own
like environment the closest term um you
won't be affected by it and then you
won't be affected even if your body
starts to break apart while you're still
alive because your mind has already
withdrawn from dependence on this but
senses they were secondary to the body
and that's something again it's so
something you would get instantaneous
but like one thought that said
everything is clear it basically is
something you have to keep doing because
it's not about again all these truths
are in a way obvious and that's not the
problem the problem is that your actions
your choices your intentions are
choosing to ignore them that's it that's
why I keep repeating Abijah it's not a
metaphysical ignorance or or a mystery
or a secret behind the veil of maya or
something that you need to discern no
it's your everyday attitude in regard to
your everyday experience when you choose
to ignore things that undermine your
your gratuitous desire your gratuitous
your will or your gratuitous need for
distraction that's it you stop ignoring
these things you will
you will you will automatically then be
removing layers and layers and layers of
your last aversion and delusion that's
it and you can see ignoring it's not on
the level of just being mindful every
second of your life no to the level of
your intentions your intentions
determined whether there is lust
whether you're acting out of lust or out
of non last absence of lust so when I
say you practice mindfulness of these
things I don't mean you keep repeating
to yourself and present the present I'm
sitting and talking about you know you
maintain the knowledge of an enduring
state of mind that determines your
intention that's how you don't ignore
you don't ignore where your intentions
are rooted because we're not ignoring
where your intentions are rooted you
will you won't be able to act carelessly
out of them because action is result of
your intention so if you're mindful of
where your intention is rooted you're by
default mindful where your action would
be rooted if you were to perform it so
then you abstain from it if it's
unwholesome and that's it
you stick to that fundamental principle
and you would prevent your mind from
gratuitous maintenance of lust diversion
and distraction that's it so that's why
that a Vidya is is something you do not
something you don't know you need to
figure out it's it's well okay you can
not know what you're supposed to do sure
that also comes under the Vita but it's
really more of an attitude you maintain
your the Vita through the attitude of
ignoring the nature of things like
through acting out of sense of self for
example you maintain the ignorant that
your experience cannot belong to you you
maintain the ignorant of Renata and you
can see it's mutually exclusive by not
acting out of sense itself
well you're closer to understanding the
nature of an author so you can't have it
both ways you can't be like oh I am NOT
acting out of sense of self but I still
have a sense of self that is mine that
belongs to me so it's either or you
either with the grain of ignorance or
against the grain of ignorance if you
stopping and the so it's noddings incidental that
and the so it's noddings incidental that
it's certainly the beginning all the
attitudes they go against the ignorance
are pretty much the attitude they will
cause you lots of anxiety lots of dread
lots of fear lots of doubt hindrances
because that is the Mara's defense he
doesn't want you to stop ignoring that's
how he keeps you bind but to the to the
experience that you don't really own and
that's where for most people the
spiritual practice just becomes the
extension of their sensuality you know
if your spiritual practice is not
undoing your dark your anxiety not
through avoiding but through being
unaffected by it so in the face of
anxiety you're not afraid that's why you know
you're not afraid that's why you know
okay well this is certainly closer to
the truth then if I refuse to admit that
I'm still liable to anxiety for example
and then my my practice is just finding
sort of colourful distractions in a
spiritual nature these cards they're
spiritual things
meditation experiences devotional
whatever else practices quite often are
fully rooted Indian just having
something more meaningful to do but
you're equally depending on having
something to do which is what keeps you
floating in an attitude of ignoring that
prevents you from facing the truth of
anxiety so why are doing so that remains
so by undoing you're by not maintaining
your attitude ignoring you will be
certain initially experiencing more
anxiety less confidence more doubt
because you're undoing no doubt
confidence absence of anxiety that was
based upon ignoring and that initial on
doing will be unpleasant but then once
you go through with it
and you would go through with it if your
behavior has been developed as any fewer
virtues not giving in to the gross acts
of last aversion or distraction that's
already a form of strength a form of
container that can then enable you to
contain the varying xiety or dread or
doubt or whatever hindrance has been
sort of stirred up on account of you
facing the reality of things and when I
say reality I mean the nature of them
so in a way you want to start
undermining testing your sense of safety
that you have now because if it were
truly true safety of being unable to
suffer on account of anxiety suffer on
account of doubt or suffer on account of
hindrances then it will stand the test
but if it's not that kind of safety like
safety of wisdom safety of liberation
you will be experiencing a degree of
anxiety or fear and that's the practice
then you need lines the work for you
perfectly so say like practically now
say you start questioning sent to safety
and yeah there's a bit of insight you
realize yeah you can you can you can get
sick somebody could come burn your house
take your way kill you whatever those
are possibilities and you choose to
dwell in them not because of some sort
of morbid fascination you just develop
them because they counter your indolence
and your complacency there is the
automatic response if you don't question
those thing if you don't think about
those things you only do it for the
practical purpose of this passion
because you can't be emotionally
invested in something that's you know
50/50 you might be taken away okay well
I better be careful how much I commit to
it because you might disappear the next
moment but if you just ignore that fact
you start to assume no it's gonna be
tomorrow of course justjust think
positive just think it's gonna be there
forever for as long as I need it then
yeah of course that's the attitude
you're gonna develop and then you'll be
acting accordingly as if yeah you're
your own master you're gonna live
forever last forever things will stay
forever as long as you want them and
even people say no of course we all know
we're gonna die no they still assume the
sense of self we'll live forever
that's very often the case so you want
to be reflecting on these opposing
themes just to question that sense of
nature it is safety
there was based entirely on ignoring the
possibility of these things because yeah
it's fifty-fifty with everything where
you gonna be alive or not tomorrow it's
50/50 but you choose are now probably alive
but you choose are now probably alive
what why did you choose that thought
because you might not be a lot death
might be hanging no it is actually and
you know over all of us so it's certain
you just don't know exactly when so why
do you then keep investing your
attention and choosing based upon as if
you're gonna you you will see the old
age why is that there's absolutely no
justification for that so then you wanna
just practice mindfulness of that not to
the point of all I want to die but to
the point of okay I'll practice enough
so I just stopped luxuriously assuming
that I will live for 50 years because
it's 50/50 that's it you don't need to
push it further you don't need to prove
yourself that you will die either you
just need to stay with that very
pleasant and kind of ambiguous 50/50
that's it because if you stay with it
that will become your theme which means
you won't be able to act as if you're
gonna live forever which means already a
great deal of passion anger irritation
righteous indignation need for
distraction it will be uprooted because
you remove the basis for it basis for
its growth so that's how that's how
these these contemplations are done
rightly now like develop like up like a
full-on mental obsession of like that
die or die or die no that becoming
equally mechanical equally ignorant
you're just trying to replace one thing
with the other you practice it only to
the extent of putting a question what
you've been taking for granted not
overdoing it and that's why it's the
middle way you need to discern that
initially ambiguous ground of it might
be it might not be either way he won't
be for me as some of the said to say but
not like it will not be for me I
guarantee no he might be might not
either way it's not for me as in I
cannot own it so I might live tomorrow I
may not live tomorrow either way it's
not mine because if it were mine I will
know for sure that I will live tomorrow
but you don't so the whole practice of
like questioning the certainty of things
is the only so you're you remove the
basis for acting out of passion towards
the thing and that basis is you must
take it for granted it is yours that you
are in its control and it's gonna be
there for as long as you want it to be
and again if you if you if you have
trouble grasping this thing take
something simpler like say there is like
a like a certain I don't know say
undertaking if I comedian somebody comes
to you and ask you for to invest a great
amount of work or finances or whatever
into something they well they won't
reward you in a great sense so it's not
like a gamble taking on risk to get more
it's more like are you gonna build this
house are you gonna spend lots of time
building whereby you agree did at any
point of your work investment it will be
torn down by somebody so you would
consider you would well if you have no
choice like you say you can't say no to
it you must do it how would you be doing
it how would you be going about that
undertaking if fundamental sort of state
of it it's not up to you if somebody can
in the middle of your work in the middle
of your commitment in the middle of your
investment can just wipe it away but you
have no choice but you have to do it you
can't say okay I'm not gonna even start
that no you have to start so you realize
you have no choice about doing things
but you certainly have a choice about
how much you get invested in your doing
how much passion you allow how far you
allowed for passion to take you out
there in your project in your fantasy of
I can't wait for this finished product
and actually anything falls into this
example I'm giving starting a family
maintaining a family ambition work study
even be being a monk like for many
people would become like oh I'm gonna
develop this you know practicing great
monastry and disciples like not
necessarily crudely but kind of
implicitly the monks life takes you this
the monks life takes you this
you know whatever ambitious undertaking
of spreading Dhamma now if you keep
yourself in check in a sense that you
realize that doesn't matter how much you
invest it doesn't matter how much you
value it if it's taken away you won't be
able to prevent it there will
automatically then automatically it will
sort of dampen the amount of passion you
can invest in it it will prevent you
from from sort of losing perspective on
it and you maintain that you can
maintain that action you got everything
whatever you are about to do even if
it's a small thing not a massive
undertaking that takes years or
something like that just just a smaller
day-to-day tasks if you don't forget
that your life can be taken away at any
point of that invested effort in a
certain task means there won't be any
passion to follow your effort of
performing the task which means you're
already practicing a form of equanimity
and indifference towards the task
because you don't lose the perspective
fundamental impermanence of it that's it
you don't have to keep saying - so I was
gonna be taking away it's gonna be taken
away all you need to do is don't forget
that it could be taken away that's it
that's more than enough and you clarify
that theme you clarify you fortify the
basis for non passion non aversion and
non distraction
so that comes back to that sense of
safety you feel safety when you ignore
the risks of your Undertaker
that's what your safety is based upon
but most people say it is based upon
ignorance of the possibility of being it
otherwise which is too unpleasant to
develop so that's why getting wisdom and
developing mental strength goes
hand-in-hand mental strength as in
Samadhi being able to maintain the
composure goes hand-in-hand because if
you're not able to maintain the
composure of a certain theme the
slightest site of often of an Ag theme
that might cause anxiety you'll be
looking away and that's a problem so
that's why I stopped practicing sense
restraint verbal distrained
so then you can actually have a mental
restraint of running away like as the
Buddha said like the the weak the weak
horse or the elephant that they get
scared you've just by the by the sound
of the battle he doesn't even see it let
alone gets into the fight he's already
running away
laying it just at the sound of the
enemy's drums but it's not a given you
are responsible for choosing to run away
so if you run away at the sound of the
enemy's drums okay start exposing
yourself to the sound of enemy drums and
we'd hold the tendency to run away take
it on a bit bit by bit then you might be
able to take their own then you run away
the sight of the drums at the side of
the enemy then you work with that and
then in the end you'll be in the battle
and you won't be running away and it's
not always a battle but when it does
come you don't run away that's the point
and you won't run away if your behavior
is based on Sealand virtue if you're
developing it right if you practice in
sense restraint you won't be leaking
that container I mentioned early and
that's how your sense of safety will
then no no depend on presence or absence
of enemy presence of absence of threat
of threat no it would it will basically
depend on your understanding of nature
of things oh this is not mine so why
would I need to be
anxious about protecting it and
everything your senses are not yours but
again you can see our senses in online
but I keep acting out of the sense of
self sense of ownership of the senses so
you can say what you want oh yes
everything is impermanent what the
science has proven impermanence we all
understand in permanence the good was
right you still act out of your sense of
appropriation which means what you're
saying are just empty hollow phrases if
you truly understand in permanence your
impenetrable to fear and anxiety because
things that are liable to be destroyed
are not your concern
and that's like that I remember the suit
I don't know which one he was he was the
that monk who was going around the
forest saying what a joy what a delight
and people heard him mother monks heard
him and they thought oh you must be
thinking about his lay life and he's
saying well the trying to like there was
he's not happy being a monk so they when
they told the Buddha they would have
called him and said is it true that he
was saying this is true why is that he's
because you think about layoffs oh no no
no quite the opposite he said when I
used to be lame and I was a prince
whatever in line to the throne and I
didn't have a moment of peace because I
was always fearing for my life so I had
guards guarding my palaces guarding my
doors guarding me a day guarding me at
night cuz he was a good likelihood
somebody is gonna make an attempt in my
life to take my place in line for the
throne so I was living in constant fear
constant anxiety constant defense of
things that I deemed mine and things
that I deemed I'm entitled to the throne
and all the value and stuff that comes
with but then he gave it a lot became a
monk became another hunt he said that
now I'm living in this completely wild
forest with wild animals tigers and
elephants and snakes he's a good
likelihood I might lose my life quickly
yet I have zero fear because I
understood the Dhamma as in he he
stopped protecting things that are
unprotectable your life your senses your
existence he gave it up and he said it's
a tremendous joy that's what he goes
around the forest saying what a joy what
a joy how much I used to defend the
invest in self-defense through all sorts
of gods and everything else and I was so
unhappy and now I'm liable to die next
moment and I experienced complete
happiness nothing for me to defend never was and
nothing for me to defend never was and
that's pretty much all to it